Hello, welcome back to our course. And today we are going to talk about programming in R. Alright, so let us talk first about functions. Functions implement tasks
you want to do repeatedly, and they help to get our code cleaner and modularize it.
So basically here, I define a function, myfun, through function() and then through passing parameters to it. So basically here, my function
returns X times X. And then the return statement terminates the function and returns the value inside the parenthesis.
So here, now I could call a function. How do I call a function? So basically, I type the name of the function, and I pass the parameter.
And then here, in the second call, I specifically ask for the name. So basically, I pass
the parameter with its name. Functions may take several parameters.
And different parameters are separated by comma. So here, I define another function.
A function with two parameters, X and A, and then inside my function, I define this r, which is A times sin of X.
And then I return r. And you can see that
once I call my function, then I pass these two parameters.
So, when naming and calling parameters. the order doesn't matter. So we can see that I can call my function by first stating X, then A, then I could call my function by first stating A and X.
And the output is the same. Here, you can see that I could also define my function
without using curly brackets if the function is short.
But usually, this way, with a curly bracket, it's a very good way to define functions, because it's very easy to read
what you have written in your script. Functions may have optional parameters, and optional parameters have default values.
We can call the function with or without the optional parameter. So here, A is an optional parameter with default 1. And then, once again, I define my function with X, a regular parameter,
and A, a default parameter. So here, what can we see? I passed my function pi over 2, 2, so I provide a different value of A.
But I could also use a default value of A, so without
passing A at all. A function can return an R data structure
basically of any type. Scalar, vector, matrix, data frame, array, list.
Whatever you defined it to return. Here, I would like to have a function with two parameters.
One regular, one optional. And then I define these two elements, R1 and R2.
And here, I would like to return a list with two named elements, they are named R1 and R2, and indeed, once I call this function, and I pass the parameter
as an output, I get a list with two elements, R1 and R2.
We could call the same function in different ways. So here, you can see that I defined a function myfun4
with 3 parameters, two are default parameters, one is a regular parameter, and I'm returning this vector of R1 and R2. And here, in the first call, I'm just calling this function, and I pass X.
A and B are defaults. Here, I'm, calling this function, I pass X, A and B explicitly.
Then, I call the function, and then I pass X and A,
and B is given as a default. Here, similarly, I pass X,
I pass A, and B is given as a default. On the other hand, here I pass X,
and I pass B, but A is given as a default.
Functions shouldn't depend on variables defined outside of it. And then functions should only provide an output, but not change
anything unintentionally, so no side effects. So, this is a function, and this is an example how we shouldn't really define the function. So, first of all, you can see that this function
takes as an output only one parameter. But first, inside, without telling anyone
it changes settings of PAR for plotting. And then, it uses Y, which was defined outside of it.
So, basically here, we would get an error that if we hadn't defined Y, then we'd get an error that
the function cannot be executed, because Y is not defined. Here, it's a good practice to
introduce this on.exit() expression/function inside of our functions, because,
basically, it runs the expression right before the function finishes, whether it ends normally,
returns early, or errors. And then, for multiple
on.exit() calls, we use add=TRUE. So, how to do it better? So, how to define function in a better way?
First of all, I'll pass two parameters here, X and Y.
And then, here you can see that I save the graphics setting.
And then you can see that now I passed this graphic setting to my on.exit. So basically, it means that I would restore them
To my default setting on exit from this function. Then I make a plot, one by two,
and then we have the first plot, and then the second plot.
Alright, now let us talk about set operations. We can perform set operations on vectors, so here let us define two vectors, A and B.
So if I would like to check which elements of A are in B, I could just check it using this percentage sign and in, so I check if A is in B, and we have false to true, because basically 1 is not in B.
Then I could create a union, so basically all elements glued together, then the intersection, so basically elements both in A and B.
And then the set difference, so elements not in both vectors, so this is one. Thank you!